In the first episode I made, I said that we will use Linux, because it allows us to have
在第一集里，我说我们将使用Linux，
a look at the Linux Kernel source code.
是因为它允许我们看 Linux内核 的源代码。
In this video we will learn what syscalls are.
在这个视频中，我们将了解什么是SysCalls(系统调用)。
And we will try to understand what user-mode and kernel-mode means, by having a look at
我们将通过观察，一个特定的内核函数 "copy_from_user"，
a specific kernel function copy_from_user.
来了解用户模式和内核模式的含义。
If you have ever wondered what it means to have an operating system in a more technical
如果你曾经想知道拥有一个更为技术性的操作系统，意味着什么。
way, I hope I can show you some very interesting stuff.
那么，我希望我能为你，展示一些非常有趣的东西。
You may have seen pictures where it says user-mode and kernel-mode.
您可能看到过显示用户模式和内核模式的图片。
Or those circles with ring-0, ring-1 and so forth.
或者那些带 ring-0, ring-1 的圆等等。
They introduce this stuff in school and even as a kid who knew how to program, I had noooo
他们在学校介绍这些东西，即使是一个孩子，也能知道如何编程，
imagination of what that actually means.
我也想过，这到底想表达什么。
You may even have heard that syscalls are an interface between those two worlds...
您甚至可能听说，SysCalls是这两个世界之间的接口…
So let’s start by looking at what kind of syscalls exist.
所以，让我们先看看存在哪种类型的SysCalls 。
And again, you can read about syscalls in the linux manual.
同样，您可以阅读Linux手册中，的 SysCalls。
So ‘man syscalls’.
所以“man SysCalls ”。
It says here, that “system call is the fundamental interface between an application and the Linux
这里说，“SysCalls 是应用程序和Linux内核之间的基本接口“
kernel.” and “System calls are generally not invoked directly, but rather via wrapper
和”SysCalls 通常不是直接调用的，而是通过glibc中的包装函数，所调用的。
functions in glibc”.
”。
“Often the glibc wrapper function is quite thin, doing little work other than copying
“通常glibc包装器函数很薄，在调用 SysCalls 之前，
arguments to the right registers before invoking the system call”.
除了复制参数到寄存器之外，几乎不做任何工作。
Invoking the system call.
调用 SysCalls (是什么呢?)。
Mhhh...
嗯…
We will find out what that means soon.
我们很快就会知道。
Further down we find a huge list of available system calls.
再往下看，我们会发现一个巨大的列表，有关可用的 SysCalls。
I mentioned in earlier videos that the libc function printf, is just a fancy wrapper around
我在前面的视频中提到，libc函数printf，只是一个
the syscall write.
花哨的SysCalls write包装函数。
And you can see that, when we use the program strace to trace all system calls.
您可以看到，当我们使用程序strace，跟踪所有SysCalls 时。
Instead of showing printf, it shows us write.
它不显示 printf，而是我们的 write。
The manpage of write says it takes 3 parameters.
write 的手册页，显示它需要3个参数。
First the file descriptor, then an address to a buffer and a count.
首先是文件描述符，然后是缓冲的地址，和一个计数。
So let’s create a simple C program that calls this function.
所以，让我们创建一个，调用这个函数的简单C程序。
The first parameter is a file descriptor.
第一个参数是文件(file)描述符。
We will talk about that value in another video, but we want it to be 1.
我们将在另一个视频中，讨论这个值，但我们希望它是 1。
Which is the file descriptor for the standard output.
表明是标准输出的文件描述符。
For the second parameter we want an address in memory that points to a string.
对于第二个参数，我们需要，指向字符串的内存地址。
We can simply write our string here, the compiler will find a place in memory for it and place
我们可以在这里简单地编写字符串，
the address of it here.
编译器将在内存中，为它找到一个位置，并在这里放置(该位置)地址。
And the last parameter will be the length.
最后一个参数是长度。
So in our case 5.
所以，在我们的例子5 中。
Now open it in radare with -d to debug it.
现在用 -d，在Radare中打开它，进行调试。
Analyse all and seek to the main function.
全面分析，寻求 main 函数。
Then print the function and place a breakpoint at the write with db.
然后打印该函数，并在用 db ，在 write 时，放置一个断点。
Then dc to start the program and switch to a visual view with V!.
然后，dc 启动程序，并切换到 "V!" 的浏览视图。
With s you can now follow this write function.
使用 s ，您现在可以跟踪这 write 写函数。
We follow some weird stuff.
我们跟踪到了些奇怪的东西。
This is the Procedure Linkage Table.
这是程序联动表(Procedure Linkage Table)。
The plt section.
PLT的部分。
It’s also sometimes called function trampoline.
它有时也被称为，函数蹦床。
Again.
再挖坑。
A topic for another video.
这又是，另一个视频的主题。
Now at some point we reach some more code.
现在，在某个时刻，我们会得到更多的代码。
This is now the actual code from the libc library.
这些是libc库中的，实际代码。
Now press s to step through this huge amount of code.
现在，按s键来步进，这庞大的代码。
I fast forward and cut a bit.
我快进了，也切一点进度。
There is sooo much stuff in this libc wrapper.
这个libc包装函数里有很多东西。
But at some point in the end it reaches the interesting part.
但，在最后的某个时刻，它来到了有趣的部分。
Here it is.
在这里。
It moves 1 into the eax register and then comes the syscall instruction.
它将 1 move 到 eax 寄存器中，然后进入syscall指令。
A peak into the intel assembler reference tells us, that this is “a Fast call to privilege
英特尔汇编程序引用的峰值，告诉我们，
level 0 system procedures.”
这是“0级系统程序的快速调用权限。”
and has the opcode 0f 05.
操作码为 0f 05。
It also says “It does so by loading RIP from the IA32_LSTAR MSR”.
它还说“它是通过从 IA32_LSTAR MSR加载 rip ，来实现的”。
MSR stands for model specific register.
MSR代表，特定型号的寄存器。
So like a jump that set’s RIP to another value to continue execution somewhere else,
所以就像一个 jump，把 RIP 设为另一个值，以便在其他地方继续执行，
it loads RIP from a model specific register (MSR).
它从特定模型的寄存器（MSR）加载 RIP。
This address was configured in this special register at some point during booting of the
这个地址是在WRMSR指令，启动系统期间的某个时间，
system through the WRMSR instruction.
配置在特定寄存器中的。
But to use this instruction you have to be in privilege level 0.
但要使用此指令，您必须处于，权限级别0。
So you cannot set this from a simple C program, because there you are in user mode, which
所以，你不能在一个简单的C程序，设置它，
is privilege level 3.
因为你在用户模式下，而它是权限级别3。
And if you wonder now how you could get into level 0 from being level 3, then the answer
如果你现在想知道，如何从3级进入0级，那么答案是
is, through instructions like syscall.
通过类似 syscall 的指令。
But then you cannot control what will be executed when you switch to level 0.
但当您切换到0级时，您将无法控制，执行的操作。
Because it will jump to a predefined address.
因为，它会 jump 到一个预先定义的地址。
So do you get now what it means to have different privilege modes, levels or rings?
那么，你现在明白拥有不同的权限模式、级别或环，意味着什么了吗？
When you turn on your computer the CPU starts in level 0.
当你打开电脑时，CPU从0级启动。
The kernel then can configure stuff like the IA32_LSTAR MSR register with an address through
然后，内核可以配置，诸如IA32_LSTAR MSR寄存器之类的东西。
the WRMSR instruction.
通过 WRMSR指令，加个地址。
Then later drops privilege of the CPU to level 3.
然后，将CPU的权限降低到级别3 三。
Now the hardware is kinda locked down.
现在，硬件有点像被锁住了。
We cannot reconfigure this register.
我们不能重新配置这个寄存器。
We cannot reconfigure the hardware.
我们无法重新配置硬件。
We only can enter level 0 again, through a syscall, but we cannot control what will be
我们只能通过SysCalls ，再次进入 0 级，
executed, because that address is fixed.
但不能控制执行的是什么，因为该地址是固定的。
Does it make sense?
这，有说得通吗，有没漏洞？
So aaaanyway...
所以，无论如何…
Let’s come back to the syscall invocation.
让我们(先)回到 SysCalls。
What we do is, we load a number in a register, in our case it was 1, and then we syscall
我们要做的是，在寄存器中，加载一个数字，在我们的情况下是 1，然后我们进行SysCalls
to enter privilege level 0 by jumping to a fixed address in the kernel.
通过跳到内核中的固定地址，来进入权限级别0。
And the kernel takes the number from the register.
内核从寄存器中，获取数字。
And it knows which syscall that is.
它知道是哪个SysCalls。
So this nice table here shows us that the write syscall has the number 1.
所以这里，这个好表格，向我们展示了 write syscall ，具有了数字 1。
So the kernel knows from a table like this, what it has to execute.
所以，内核从这样的表格中，知道它必须执行什么。
And it’s implemented in the source-code-file read_write.c
具体，它在源代码文件 read-write.c 中，实现。
And here it is.
好啦，结尾啦。
So that is what will be executed in the kernel when you invoke the write syscall.
所以，当您调用 write-syscall 时，这就是内核中，要执行的操作。
There is an awesome free book called Linux Device Drivers, which goes into great details
有一本很棒的免费书，叫做Linux设备驱动程序(Linux Device Drivers)，
how the Kernel works.
详细介绍了内核是如何工作的。
Especially how to write a device driver and kernel modules.
尤其说明了，如何编写设备驱动程序和内核模块。
And in chapter 3 section 7 it reads: “The code for read and write in scull needs
在第3章第7节中，它写道：“在scull中，用于读写的代码，
to copy a whole segment of data to or from the user address space.
需要将整个数据段，复制到用户地址空间，或从用户那复制。
This capability is offered by the following kernel functions, which copy an arbitrary
此功能，由以下内核函数提供，
array of bytes and sit at the heart of most read and write implementations”
这些函数能复制任意字节数组，占据大多数读写实现的核心”
So first, what does user address space mean.
首先，用户地址空间(user address space)是什么意思？
Maybe when you debugged some programs with gdb, you wondered how it can be, that every
也许，当你用 gdb 调试一些程序时，你想知道它是怎样的，
program seems to use the same addresses.
每一个程序似乎使用相同的地址。
Code is always at the same addresses.
代码总是在同一个地址。
Stack is always at the same addresses.
栈总是在同一个地址。
That doesn’t make sense.
这没有道理。
How can all programs use use the same addresses in memory?
所有程序，怎么会使用相同的内存地址？
Wouldn’t they overwrite each other?
它们不会互相覆盖吗？
This is why we have a MMU.
这就是我们有一个MMU的原因。
A Memory Management Unit.
内存管理单元(Memory Management Unit)。
The kernel sets up the MMU with special CPU instructions and configuration registers and
内核使用特殊的CPU指令设置MMU，
so forth.
和配置寄存器等等
And this tells the MMU how to translate between virtual and physical addresses.
这告诉MMU，如何在虚拟地址和物理地址之间进行转换。
So when you use the instruction mov eax, [0x08004200] in your C program, the MMU will know how to
因此，当您在C程序中，使用指令 "mov eax ，[0x08004200]"时，
translate this address for a given process to an actual physical address in your RAM.
MMU知道在给定进程，如何将此地址转换为，RAM中的实际物理地址。
So it might request address 0x7f527320.
所以，它可能请求地址"0x7F527320"。
But you don’t have to care about that.
但你不必担心。
The magic happens deep inside the hardware.
'魔法'，发生在硬件的深处。
This allows us to write programs without having to think about which addresses are still free.
这使我们在编写程序时，可以不必考虑哪些地址空闲。
So when you are in the kernel, after you have entered it with a syscall, you might want
因此，当您使用 SysCalls ，进入内核后，
to copy some data from user address space, for example to write it somewhere else.
您可能需要从用户地址空间复制一些数据，例如将它，写入其他地方。
To do this you can use the copy_from_user function.
要做到这一点，您可以使用“copy_from_user”函数。
And I thought it might be an interesting function to trace through the kernel source code to
还有，我认为，通过这个有趣的函数，可以跟随内核源代码，
get a feeling how the code of an operating system looks like.
了解一个操作系统代码长什么样的。
So let’s use the Linux Cross Reference, because it allows us to easily search for
所以，让我们使用 Linux 交叉引用(Cross Reference)，因为
labels.
它允许我们轻松地搜索标签。
So let’s start by looking for the function copy_from_user.
好了，让我们从'copy_from_user'函数开始。
And we get a list with multiple places this function is defined.
我们得到一个列表，这个函数被定义了多个位置。
That is so weird.
真奇怪。
Why are there multiple places for that?
为什么有多个地方？
Well if you look closely at the file path, you will notice that each different CPU architecture
Well，如果仔细观察文件路径，就会发现
has it’s own folder.
每个不同的CPU体系结构都有自己的文件夹。
So you can see here ARM, for processors that you can find in your
所以，你可以在这里看到 ARM，为你智能手机的处理器。
smartphone or POWERPC which is used by the Playstation
或是，PlayStation 3 使用的 PowerPC，
3 or the Nintendo Wii and also x86, which is probably the architecture of your computer
或者 任天堂Wii ，当然
right now.
还有，x86，这可能是你电脑的现在架构。
So the code get’s pretty crazy.
所以代码会变得疯狂起来，
And I don’t know a lot about it.
而我也不太了解。
But let’s just follow the main functions here and ignore the checks and stuff around
但是，让我们跟着这里的 main 函数，
it.
忽略检查和周围的东西。
So copy_from_user calls an underscore copy_from_user.
所以"copy_from_user"，调用了一个（下划线）"_copy_from_user"调用。
That function calls access_ok on the from parameter, which is an address the user specified,
该函数调用 from 参数的 access_ok，该参数是用户指定的地址，
in our case the address of the string we wanted to write.
在我们的例子中，是我们想写的这个字符串的地址。
And this checks if this particular process is allowed to read from the address.
而这个检查，是否允许这个特定的过程，读取地址。
Imagine if the process tries to read some secrets from another process.
试想一下，如果这个过程试图，从另一个过程中读取一些秘密。
And if everything is fine it calls underscore underscore copy_from_user.
终，如果一切正常，它会调用"__copy_from_user"。
Uhh… now it seems to split up in either 32bit or 64bit.
嗯… 现在它似乎分成32位或64位。
And because we have a 64bit ubuntu linux, let’s follow that path.
因为我们有一个64位的 Ubuntu Linux，所以让我们沿着这条路走。
This looks like just a wrapper around copy_from_user_nocheck.
这看起来就像是一个包装'copy_from_user_nocheck'的函数着用户的拷贝。
Indicating that the following functions won’t check the access rights again.
指示，以下函数将不再检查访问权限。
But luckily the kernel already did that.
但幸运的是，内核已经做了。
Ok we follow that and we arrive at a pretty big function.
好的，我们遵循这一点，我们到了一个相当大的函数。
So here is a big switch-case statements which seems to check the size we want to read from
所以这里，有一个很大的 switch语-case 语句，它似乎检查了，
the user space.
我们想要读取的用户空间的大小。
So let’s say we just wanted to read 1 byte from userspace.
假设，我们只想从用户空间中，读取1个字节。
We would be in this case 1: here.
在这种情况下，我们是 "case 1:" 这里。
So get_user_asm is a preprocessor macro.
而这个"get_user_asm"是一个预处理器宏。
This get’s into how a C file is compiled in stages.
这就是需要C文件编译，如何分阶段的知识啦。
But it’s actually very simple.
但其实很简单。
This statement is just a simple copy and replace.
这个声明(语句)，只是一个简单的复制和替换。
So it means that this code that is defined here, is just simply copied at the location
所以这意味着这里定义的代码，在编译器开始编译为机器代码之前，
it was used earlier, before the compiler starts to compile it to machine code.
只是简单地复制到它先前用过位置。
So you can basically just read it like a standard C function.
所以，你基本上可以像标准的C函数，那样阅读它。
And get_user_asm defines some actual CPU instructions.
而，'get_user_asm'定义了一些实际的CPU指令。
And this move here is the instruction that moves data from the user space into a variable
这里的 move 是，将数据从用户空间，
here.
移动到这里变量中的指令。
So itype and rtype are from the parameters up here.
因此，itype 和 rtype，来自上面的参数。
And they were set to “b” for a single byte.
它们被设置为，单字节的“b”。
And in the way how those preprocessor statements work, you just replace this text with b.
根据这些预处理器语句的工作方式，您只需用 b 替换这个文本。
So the actual instruction would look like ‘movb %2,%b1’.
所以， 实际的指令看起来像“movb %2,%b1”。
Eh so this is at&amp;t assembler syntax so it means it moves whatever %2 is into %b1.
额，这是AT&T汇编程序语法，这意味着，它将任何 %2 移动到 %b1 中。
Now this is C inline assembler syntax and it refers to the variables that are defined
现在，这是C内联汇编程序语法，它引用
down here.
定义在这里的变量。
So percentage 2 refers to the third parameter.
所以，"%2"是指第三个参数。
0, 1, 2.
0, 1, 2。
Which is the address we want to move data from.
这是我们要移动数据的来源地址。
And we want to move it into %1, which is x.
我们想把它，移到 %1，也就是x。
And that is the location we want to move it to.
这就是我们要把它移到的地方。
The move is wrapped with STAC and CLAC, which stands for set and clear ac register.
这个 move 是包裹在 STAC 和 CLAC 的，它们(缩写)代表，设置(set)和清除(clear) ac寄存器。
And it has to do with SMAP, an anti exploitation feature.
必须用 SMAP 搭配 —— 一个反漏洞功能。
And there are the raw opcodes from that instruction.
还有这些是，那个指令的原始操作码。
And below the move we see something with section fixup and assembler exception table.
在下面的移动中，我们看到了，fixup和汇编程序异常表的部分。
That goes into how the kernel handles hardware exception.
这涉及到，内核如何处理硬件异常。
But there is a great documentation I found and you can read what it does there exactly:
但我发现了一个很好的文档，您可以知道，它到底做了什么：
Anyhow.
怎么都行。
As you can see, there was no code that would somehow translate the user supplied virtual
如您所见，没有任何代码，会以某种方式
address to a real physical address.
转换用户提供的虚拟地址到实际的物理地址。
It just executes a mov.
它只是执行一个 mov。
That is because the magic happens somewhere else.
那是因为，魔法是发生在别的地方。
When the kernel executes this instruction, it will cause a page fault, because it tries
当内核执行此指令时，它将导致页面错误，
to access a virtual address.
因为它尝试访问虚拟地址。
And that is an interrupt, which means the CPU will jump to another predefined code location
这是一个中断，这意味着CPU将跳转到，另一个预定义的代码位置。
in the kernel where this exception will be handled.
在这里，内核的这些异常，会被控制。
Pretty similar how the syscall instruction made us jump to a predefined address.
这与syscall指令让我们跳转到一个预定义地址类似。
And in that page fault handler in the kernel, all the address magic with the MMU will happen.
在内核中的页面错误处理程序中，所有与MMU相关的，地址魔法都会发生。
I will not go into that, because it’s already enough information for now.
我不会深入了，因为，现在已经足够了。
But I hope this random dive into the kernel code was interesting and maybe even eye opening.
但我希望随缘深入，内核代码是有趣的，甚至可能会让人大开眼界。
So many smart people worked together on creating such a complex and amazing platform.
多少聪明的人，一起创造了这样一个复杂而神奇的平台。
Almost makes me emotional thinking about how the media celebrates new iPhone apps, while
当真正的魔法发生，几乎让我想到，
the real magic happens down here.
媒体是如何庆祝新的iPhone应用程序的。
Don’t worry if you didn’t understand everything.
如果你什么都不懂，别担心。
Hell, I even didn’t understand a lot of it.
不要难过，即便我自己甚至都不太明白。
But it’s important to just dive into some unknown stuff once in a while and get a first
但是，偶尔潜入一些未知的事物中，
glimpse of what is there.
领略其中风光是很重要的。
And I am sure that at least subconsciously you now have a feeling for what it means to
我相信，至少在潜意识里，你现在对有一个内核，。
have a Kernel.
有了一种感觉。
I start to worry a bit that I may forget to explain certain things that seem clear to
我开始有点担心，我可能会忘记解释，
me and that you guys get lost.
对我来说清晰，大家却还不了解的的事情。
So please give me feedback on how the first couple of videos of the series were for you.
所以，请给我关于这个系列的前两个视频的反馈，
And what is still unclear.
它到底怎躺，还有什么不清楚。
So I can improve and make content that helps as many people as possible.
这样，我就可以改进和制作，尽力，能帮助更多人的内容。